<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://nitish-nagesh.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://nitish-nagesh.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-12-01T02:02:35+00:00</updated><id>https://nitish-nagesh.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>Nitish Nagesh - Ph.D. Candidate in Computer Science at UC Irvine. Research in causal inference, synthetic data generation, and fairness for health and medicine applications. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Exciting Opportunities in AI, Healthcare, and Research - December 2025</title><link href="https://nitish-nagesh.github.io/blog/2025/exciting-opportunities-ai-healthcare-research/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Exciting Opportunities in AI, Healthcare, and Research - December 2025"/><published>2025-10-22T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-10-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://nitish-nagesh.github.io/blog/2025/exciting-opportunities-ai-healthcare-research</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://nitish-nagesh.github.io/blog/2025/exciting-opportunities-ai-healthcare-research/"><![CDATA[<p>As I’ve been exploring post-PhD career paths and opportunities, I’ve come across some incredible programs that align perfectly with my interests in AI, healthcare, and research. I wanted to share these opportunities with my network, as they might be relevant for other graduate students and researchers in similar fields.</p> <h2 id="-ai-based-protein-design-internship-at-insmed">🧬 AI-Based Protein Design Internship at Insmed</h2> <p><strong><a href="https://insmed.wd5.myworkdayjobs.com/en-US/EXTERNAL/details/Summer-Intern---AI-Based-Protein-Design_R2684">Insmed Summer Intern - AI-Based Protein Design</a></strong></p> <p>This is a fascinating opportunity at the intersection of AI and biotechnology. Insmed is looking for summer interns to work on AI-based protein design, which combines machine learning with structural biology. This would be perfect for someone with:</p> <ul> <li>Background in machine learning/AI</li> <li>Interest in computational biology</li> <li>Experience with protein structure prediction</li> <li>Passion for drug discovery applications</li> </ul> <p>The application process appears to be through their Workday system, and this could be an excellent stepping stone into the biotech industry.</p> <h2 id="-johnson--johnson-rd-leadership-development-program">🏥 Johnson &amp; Johnson R&amp;D Leadership Development Program</h2> <p><strong><a href="https://www.careers.jnj.com/en/jobs/r-030459/research-and-development-leadership-development-program-rdldp-2026-full-time/">J&amp;J Research and Development Leadership Development Program (RDLDP) 2026</a></strong></p> <p>This is a prestigious full-time program designed to develop future leaders in pharmaceutical R&amp;D. The RDLDP program offers:</p> <ul> <li>Rotational assignments across different R&amp;D functions</li> <li>Leadership development and mentorship</li> <li>Exposure to cutting-edge pharmaceutical research</li> <li>Potential for long-term career growth at J&amp;J</li> </ul> <p>This program would be ideal for PhD graduates looking to transition into industry leadership roles, particularly those with backgrounds in:</p> <ul> <li>Biomedical research</li> <li>Data science and analytics</li> <li>Clinical research</li> <li>Regulatory affairs</li> </ul> <h2 id="-summer-research-training-in-biomedical-big-data-science">🔬 Summer Research Training in Biomedical Big Data Science</h2> <p><strong><a href="https://docs.google.com/forms/d/e/1FAIpQLSegUfh1kfLptg6Ry42hwDjX7l36wTohQPp492zPn6xfMaNz5Q/viewform">Mount Sinai Summer Research Training Program</a></strong></p> <p>This is an intensive 10-week research program at Mount Sinai’s Center for Bioinformatics, focusing on:</p> <ul> <li>Data harmonization</li> <li>Machine learning applications in healthcare</li> <li>Cloud computing for biomedical data</li> <li>Dynamic data visualization</li> </ul> <p><strong>Key Details:</strong></p> <ul> <li><strong>Application Deadline</strong>: February 1, 2026 at 5:00 PM Eastern Time</li> <li><strong>Duration</strong>: 10 weeks (summer)</li> <li><strong>Requirements</strong>: U.S. citizen or permanent resident, undergraduate or master’s student</li> <li><strong>Location</strong>: Icahn School of Medicine at Mount Sinai, New York, NY</li> </ul> <p>This program would be perfect for students interested in biomedical data science and computational approaches to healthcare research.</p> <h2 id="-why-these-opportunities-matter">💡 Why These Opportunities Matter</h2> <p>These opportunities represent three different but complementary career paths:</p> <ol> <li><strong>Industry Innovation</strong> (Insmed) - Working on cutting-edge AI applications in drug discovery</li> <li><strong>Corporate Leadership</strong> (J&amp;J) - Developing leadership skills in pharmaceutical R&amp;D</li> <li><strong>Academic Research</strong> (Mount Sinai) - Gaining research experience in biomedical data science</li> </ol> <p>Each offers unique experiences that could shape different aspects of a career in healthcare technology and research.</p> <h2 id="-application-tips">🎯 Application Tips</h2> <p>Based on my experience applying to similar programs:</p> <ul> <li><strong>Start early</strong> - These programs have competitive application processes</li> <li><strong>Tailor your application</strong> - Highlight relevant experience in AI, healthcare, or research</li> <li><strong>Prepare strong recommendations</strong> - Many programs require letters from faculty mentors</li> <li><strong>Show passion</strong> - Demonstrate genuine interest in the specific field and company/institution</li> </ul> <h2 id="-lets-connect">🤝 Let’s Connect</h2> <p>If any of these opportunities align with your interests, I’d love to hear about your experiences applying or if you have questions about similar programs. Feel free to reach out if you’d like to discuss:</p> <ul> <li>Application strategies</li> <li>Career transitions from academia to industry</li> <li>Research opportunities in healthcare AI</li> <li>Networking in the biotech/pharma space</li> </ul> <p>These opportunities represent just a snapshot of the exciting possibilities in AI and healthcare. As the field continues to evolve, I’m excited to see how these programs will shape the next generation of researchers and industry leaders.</p> <hr/> <p><em>Have you come across any interesting opportunities in AI, healthcare, or research? I’d love to hear about them and potentially feature them in future posts!</em></p>]]></content><author><name>Nitish Nagesh</name></author><category term="opportunities"/><category term="opportunities"/><category term="AI"/><category term="healthcare"/><category term="research"/><category term="internships"/><category term="careers"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Discovering amazing opportunities in AI-based protein design, healthcare R&D leadership, and biomedical data science research programs.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Opportunities</title><link href="https://nitish-nagesh.github.io/blog/2025/opportunities/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Opportunities"/><published>2025-10-22T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-10-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://nitish-nagesh.github.io/blog/2025/opportunities</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://nitish-nagesh.github.io/blog/2025/opportunities/"><![CDATA[<h1 id="opportunities">Opportunities</h1> <p><em>This page will be updated with new opportunities as I discover them.</em></p> <hr/> <p><em>Last updated: January 2025</em></p>]]></content><author><name>Nitish Nagesh</name></author><category term="opportunities"/><category term="opportunities"/><category term="AI"/><category term="healthcare"/><category term="research"/><category term="internships"/><category term="careers"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A curated list of opportunities in AI, healthcare, and research.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Building Trustworthy AI for Health Applications</title><link href="https://nitish-nagesh.github.io/blog/2025/building-trustworthy-ai-for-health/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Building Trustworthy AI for Health Applications"/><published>2025-01-15T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://nitish-nagesh.github.io/blog/2025/building-trustworthy-ai-for-health</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://nitish-nagesh.github.io/blog/2025/building-trustworthy-ai-for-health/"><![CDATA[<p>As a Ph.D. candidate specializing in trustworthy AI for health applications, I’ve witnessed firsthand the transformative potential of artificial intelligence in healthcare. However, with great power comes great responsibility—especially when dealing with sensitive health data and life-critical decisions.</p> <h2 id="the-trust-challenge-in-healthcare-ai">The Trust Challenge in Healthcare AI</h2> <p>Healthcare AI systems face unique challenges that go beyond traditional machine learning applications:</p> <ul> <li><strong>Bias amplification</strong>: Historical healthcare disparities can be perpetuated by AI systems</li> <li><strong>Explainability requirements</strong>: Clinicians need to understand AI recommendations</li> <li><strong>Causal reasoning</strong>: Correlation doesn’t imply causation, especially in health outcomes</li> <li><strong>Fairness across populations</strong>: Ensuring equitable outcomes across diverse patient groups</li> </ul> <h2 id="my-research-approach-causal-fairness">My Research Approach: Causal Fairness</h2> <p>In my recent work on <strong>FairCauseSyn</strong>, we developed a framework for generating causally fair synthetic data using large language models. This approach addresses a critical gap in healthcare AI: how do we create training data that doesn’t perpetuate existing biases?</p> <h3 id="key-insights">Key Insights:</h3> <ol> <li><strong>Causal graphs matter</strong>: Understanding the causal relationships between variables is crucial for fair AI</li> <li><strong>Synthetic data can help</strong>: When real data is biased, carefully generated synthetic data can provide fairer training sets</li> <li><strong>LLMs as data generators</strong>: Large language models can be fine-tuned to generate causally consistent synthetic data</li> </ol> <h2 id="practical-applications">Practical Applications</h2> <p>This research has direct implications for:</p> <ul> <li><strong>Clinical decision support systems</strong></li> <li><strong>Drug discovery and development</strong></li> <li><strong>Personalized treatment recommendations</strong></li> <li><strong>Health outcome predictions</strong></li> </ul> <h2 id="looking-forward">Looking Forward</h2> <p>The future of healthcare AI lies in systems that are not just accurate, but also fair, explainable, and causally sound. As we continue to develop these technologies, it’s crucial that we prioritize patient safety and equity.</p> <hr/> <p><em>This post is part of my ongoing research on trustworthy AI for health applications. For more insights, follow my work on <a href="https://github.com/nitish-nagesh">GitHub</a> and connect with me on <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/nitish-nagesh/">LinkedIn</a>.</em></p> <p><strong>LinkedIn Cross-Post</strong>: This article was also published on <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/nitish-nagesh/">LinkedIn</a> for broader professional engagement. Feel free to share your thoughts and experiences with healthcare AI in the comments!</p>]]></content><author><name>Nitish Nagesh</name></author><category term="research"/><category term="AI"/><category term="health"/><category term="causal-inference"/><category term="fairness"/><category term="research"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Exploring the challenges and opportunities in developing fair, explainable AI systems for healthcare, with insights from my research on causal inference and bias mitigation.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Improving Access to Graduate Education: Creating a Consolidated PhD Positions Resource</title><link href="https://nitish-nagesh.github.io/blog/2025/improving-access-to-graduate-education/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Improving Access to Graduate Education: Creating a Consolidated PhD Positions Resource"/><published>2025-01-15T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://nitish-nagesh.github.io/blog/2025/improving-access-to-graduate-education</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://nitish-nagesh.github.io/blog/2025/improving-access-to-graduate-education/"><![CDATA[<p>When I was applying to PhD programs, I encountered a significant gap in available resources. While CSrankings lists professors, their research areas, and links to their websites, there was no consolidated list that contained all potential PhD openings at universities like UC Irvine.</p> <h2 id="the-problem">The Problem</h2> <p>Prospective graduate students face several challenges when researching PhD opportunities:</p> <ul> <li><strong>Scattered information</strong>: Faculty openings are posted across multiple platforms</li> <li><strong>Time-consuming research</strong>: Students must visit individual faculty websites</li> <li><strong>Missed opportunities</strong>: Important deadlines and openings can be overlooked</li> <li><strong>Limited diversity</strong>: Lack of centralized information disproportionately affects underrepresented students</li> </ul> <h2 id="our-solution">Our Solution</h2> <p>Together with my fellow Ph.D. student <a href="https://github.com/nitish-nagesh/uci-ics-phd-positions">Alagappan Ramanathan</a>, we created a comprehensive resource for UC Irvine’s Donald Bren School of Information and Computer Sciences PhD positions.</p> <h3 id="what-we-built">What We Built</h3> <p>Our <a href="https://github.com/nitish-nagesh/uci-ics-phd-positions">GitHub repository</a> provides:</p> <ul> <li><strong>Consolidated listings</strong> of all PhD openings at UC Irvine ICS</li> <li><strong>Faculty research areas</strong> and contact information</li> <li><strong>Application deadlines</strong> and requirements</li> <li><strong>Direct links</strong> to faculty profiles and research groups</li> </ul> <p>This resource is particularly relevant for prospective students applying for Fall 2025 admissions.</p> <h2 id="impact-and-mission">Impact and Mission</h2> <p>Our mission is to <strong>improve access to information for prospective students</strong>, thereby contributing to a more diverse applicant pool in computer science graduate programs.</p> <h3 id="key-benefits">Key Benefits:</h3> <ol> <li><strong>Democratized access</strong>: All students, regardless of background, can easily find opportunities</li> <li><strong>Time savings</strong>: Reduces research time from weeks to hours</li> <li><strong>Comprehensive coverage</strong>: No missed opportunities due to scattered information</li> <li><strong>Community building</strong>: Encourages collaboration across campus organizations</li> </ol> <h2 id="community-support">Community Support</h2> <p>We’re grateful for the support and feedback from:</p> <ul> <li><strong>Sara Heimann</strong> for her valuable feedback</li> <li><strong>Jennifer Hammelman</strong> for inspiration through Project SHORT</li> <li><strong>Campus organizations</strong>: WICS UCI, Artificial Intelligence at UCI, ACM@UCI, @Data @ UCI, UCI ANTrepreneur Center</li> </ul> <h2 id="future-expansion">Future Expansion</h2> <p>Our vision extends beyond UC Irvine. We aim to expand this resource to:</p> <ul> <li><strong>Other California universities</strong></li> <li><strong>Universities across the United States</strong></li> <li><strong>Additional information</strong>: Faculty Google Scholar pages, Twitter accounts, and latest research updates</li> </ul> <h2 id="call-to-action">Call to Action</h2> <p>We need help from the community to:</p> <ul> <li><strong>Curate lists for other schools</strong> (deadlines are approaching!)</li> <li><strong>Add faculty information</strong>: Google Scholar links, Twitter accounts, latest research</li> <li><strong>Share with networks</strong>: Help spread the word to prospective students</li> </ul> <p><strong>Interested in contributing to DEI efforts in graduate education?</strong> Please reach out to me at <strong>nnagesh1@uci.edu</strong>.</p> <h2 id="technical-implementation">Technical Implementation</h2> <p>The resource is built using:</p> <ul> <li><strong>GitHub Pages</strong> for easy access and collaboration</li> <li><strong>Markdown format</strong> for simple editing and maintenance</li> <li><strong>Open source approach</strong> to encourage community contributions</li> <li><strong>Structured data</strong> for easy navigation and search</li> </ul> <h2 id="looking-forward">Looking Forward</h2> <p>This project represents more than just a resource—it’s about <strong>breaking down barriers</strong> in graduate education and creating pathways for talented students from all backgrounds to pursue advanced degrees in computer science.</p> <p>By making information more accessible, we’re not just helping individual students; we’re contributing to a more diverse and innovative future for the field of computer science.</p> <hr/> <p><em>This post was originally shared on <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/posts/nitish-nagesh_github-nitish-nageshuci-ics-phd-positions-activity-7272841692670533633-a3Rp">LinkedIn</a> and has been adapted for this blog. For more insights on graduate education and research, follow my work on <a href="https://github.com/nitish-nagesh">GitHub</a> and connect with me on <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/nitish-nagesh/">LinkedIn</a>.</em></p> <p><strong>LinkedIn Cross-Post</strong>: This article was also published on <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/posts/nitish-nagesh_github-nitish-nageshuci-ics-phd-positions-activity-7272841692670533633-a3Rp">LinkedIn</a> for broader professional engagement. Feel free to share your thoughts and experiences with graduate school applications in the comments!</p>]]></content><author><name>Nitish Nagesh</name></author><category term="research"/><category term="education"/><category term="diversity"/><category term="graduate-school"/><category term="research"/><category term="leadership"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[How my fellow Ph.D. student Alagappan Ramanathan and I created a comprehensive resource for prospective students applying to UC Irvine's Computer Science programs, with plans to expand nationwide.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Exciting Opportunities in AI, Healthcare, and Research - December 2025</title><link href="https://nitish-nagesh.github.io/blog/2024/exciting-opportunities-ai-healthcare-research/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Exciting Opportunities in AI, Healthcare, and Research - December 2025"/><published>2024-12-15T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-12-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://nitish-nagesh.github.io/blog/2024/exciting-opportunities-ai-healthcare-research</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://nitish-nagesh.github.io/blog/2024/exciting-opportunities-ai-healthcare-research/"><![CDATA[<p>As I’ve been exploring post-PhD career paths and opportunities, I’ve come across some incredible programs that align perfectly with my interests in AI, healthcare, and research. I wanted to share these opportunities with my network, as they might be relevant for other graduate students and researchers in similar fields.</p> <h2 id="-ai-based-protein-design-internship-at-insmed">🧬 AI-Based Protein Design Internship at Insmed</h2> <p><strong><a href="https://insmed.wd5.myworkdayjobs.com/en-US/EXTERNAL/details/Summer-Intern---AI-Based-Protein-Design_R2684">Insmed Summer Intern - AI-Based Protein Design</a></strong></p> <p>This is a fascinating opportunity at the intersection of AI and biotechnology. Insmed is looking for summer interns to work on AI-based protein design, which combines machine learning with structural biology. This would be perfect for someone with:</p> <ul> <li>Background in machine learning/AI</li> <li>Interest in computational biology</li> <li>Experience with protein structure prediction</li> <li>Passion for drug discovery applications</li> </ul> <p>The application process appears to be through their Workday system, and this could be an excellent stepping stone into the biotech industry.</p> <h2 id="-johnson--johnson-rd-leadership-development-program">🏥 Johnson &amp; Johnson R&amp;D Leadership Development Program</h2> <p><strong><a href="https://www.careers.jnj.com/en/jobs/r-030459/research-and-development-leadership-development-program-rdldp-2026-full-time/">J&amp;J Research and Development Leadership Development Program (RDLDP) 2026</a></strong></p> <p>This is a prestigious full-time program designed to develop future leaders in pharmaceutical R&amp;D. The RDLDP program offers:</p> <ul> <li>Rotational assignments across different R&amp;D functions</li> <li>Leadership development and mentorship</li> <li>Exposure to cutting-edge pharmaceutical research</li> <li>Potential for long-term career growth at J&amp;J</li> </ul> <p>This program would be ideal for PhD graduates looking to transition into industry leadership roles, particularly those with backgrounds in:</p> <ul> <li>Biomedical research</li> <li>Data science and analytics</li> <li>Clinical research</li> <li>Regulatory affairs</li> </ul> <h2 id="-summer-research-training-in-biomedical-big-data-science">🔬 Summer Research Training in Biomedical Big Data Science</h2> <p><strong><a href="https://docs.google.com/forms/d/e/1FAIpQLSegUfh1kfLptg6Ry42hwDjX7l36wTohQPp492zPn6xfMaNz5Q/viewform">Mount Sinai Summer Research Training Program</a></strong></p> <p>This is an intensive 10-week research program at Mount Sinai’s Center for Bioinformatics, focusing on:</p> <ul> <li>Data harmonization</li> <li>Machine learning applications in healthcare</li> <li>Cloud computing for biomedical data</li> <li>Dynamic data visualization</li> </ul> <p><strong>Key Details:</strong></p> <ul> <li><strong>Application Deadline</strong>: February 1, 2026 at 5:00 PM Eastern Time</li> <li><strong>Duration</strong>: 10 weeks (summer)</li> <li><strong>Requirements</strong>: U.S. citizen or permanent resident, undergraduate or master’s student</li> <li><strong>Location</strong>: Icahn School of Medicine at Mount Sinai, New York, NY</li> </ul> <p>This program would be perfect for students interested in biomedical data science and computational approaches to healthcare research.</p> <h2 id="-why-these-opportunities-matter">💡 Why These Opportunities Matter</h2> <p>These opportunities represent three different but complementary career paths:</p> <ol> <li><strong>Industry Innovation</strong> (Insmed) - Working on cutting-edge AI applications in drug discovery</li> <li><strong>Corporate Leadership</strong> (J&amp;J) - Developing leadership skills in pharmaceutical R&amp;D</li> <li><strong>Academic Research</strong> (Mount Sinai) - Gaining research experience in biomedical data science</li> </ol> <p>Each offers unique experiences that could shape different aspects of a career in healthcare technology and research.</p> <h2 id="-application-tips">🎯 Application Tips</h2> <p>Based on my experience applying to similar programs:</p> <ul> <li><strong>Start early</strong> - These programs have competitive application processes</li> <li><strong>Tailor your application</strong> - Highlight relevant experience in AI, healthcare, or research</li> <li><strong>Prepare strong recommendations</strong> - Many programs require letters from faculty mentors</li> <li><strong>Show passion</strong> - Demonstrate genuine interest in the specific field and company/institution</li> </ul> <h2 id="-lets-connect">🤝 Let’s Connect</h2> <p>If any of these opportunities align with your interests, I’d love to hear about your experiences applying or if you have questions about similar programs. Feel free to reach out if you’d like to discuss:</p> <ul> <li>Application strategies</li> <li>Career transitions from academia to industry</li> <li>Research opportunities in healthcare AI</li> <li>Networking in the biotech/pharma space</li> </ul> <p>These opportunities represent just a snapshot of the exciting possibilities in AI and healthcare. As the field continues to evolve, I’m excited to see how these programs will shape the next generation of researchers and industry leaders.</p> <hr/> <p><em>Have you come across any interesting opportunities in AI, healthcare, or research? I’d love to hear about them and potentially feature them in future posts!</em></p>]]></content><author><name>Nitish Nagesh</name></author><category term="opportunities"/><category term="opportunities"/><category term="AI"/><category term="healthcare"/><category term="research"/><category term="internships"/><category term="careers"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Discovering amazing opportunities in AI-based protein design, healthcare R&D leadership, and biomedical data science research programs.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Opportunities</title><link href="https://nitish-nagesh.github.io/blog/2024/opportunities/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Opportunities"/><published>2024-12-15T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-12-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://nitish-nagesh.github.io/blog/2024/opportunities</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://nitish-nagesh.github.io/blog/2024/opportunities/"><![CDATA[<h1 id="opportunities">Opportunities</h1> <p><em>This page will be updated with new opportunities as I discover them.</em></p> <hr/> <p><em>Last updated: January 2025</em></p>]]></content><author><name>Nitish Nagesh</name></author><category term="opportunities"/><category term="opportunities"/><category term="AI"/><category term="healthcare"/><category term="research"/><category term="internships"/><category term="careers"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A curated list of opportunities in AI, healthcare, and research.]]></summary></entry></feed>